<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[GARETH VEALE.]]></title><description><![CDATA[Gareth Veale.]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 09:03:47 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Dune, Frank Herbert]]></title><description><![CDATA[I read the first part of this sci-fi series in 2020, during the first lockdown in the UK. It’s one of few books that I couldn’t put down…]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev/dune/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://garethveale.dev/dune/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I read the first part of this sci-fi series in 2020, during the first lockdown in the UK. It’s one of few books that I couldn’t put down. This series is at the cross-section of science, philosophy, technology, politics, and war. There’s tons of themes, ranging from geology to conciousness, through to psychology and epistomology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m almost finished with the second part - Dune Messiah - and am delighted it’s as good as the first. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I haven’t read Game of Thrones, I get the impression a lot of the themes are drawn from these novels (the first part was written in 1965). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language can be quite challenging at times, which I appreciate, and am glad I’m reading the second part on my kindle (the dictionary feature is 👌 ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not even going to say if you enjoy sci-fi read this, if you enjoy reading, read this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a movie being released this year, with a huge cast (and Hans Zimmer scored), based on the first half of the first book, giving you another reason to read it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my favourite quotes from the second book are below, even these demonstrate how well written these books are - strong 10/10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Belief can be manipulated. Only knowledge is dangerous.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I must not fear. Fear is the mind-killer. Fear is the little-death that brings total obliteration. I will face my fear …”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No matter how exotic human civilization becomes, no matter the developments of life and society nor the complexity of the machine/human interface, there always come interludes of lonely power when the course of humankind, the very future of humankind, depends upon the relatively simple actions of single individuals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s but a thin line between many an enemy and many a friend,”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Moore's Law - is it dead?]]></title><description><![CDATA[What is Moore’s law? Is it dead? (And why this matters) In case you weren’t aware, it’s 2020. Computer technology has been accelerating…]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev/moores-law/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://garethveale.dev/moores-law/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 23 Jan 2021 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;What is Moore’s law? Is it dead? (And why this matters)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you weren’t aware, it’s 2020. Computer technology has been accelerating rapidly for decades. How can we explain this growth? Is this rate of change ever going to slow? Introducing Moore’s law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an observation by Gordon Moore in 1965, stating that the number of transistors in a silicon chip doubles every year. As you can see, this rate of acceleration led to exponential growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/79ee6/transistor.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 74.32432432432432%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAPCAIAAABr+ngCAAAACXBIWXMAAAsSAAALEgHS3X78AAABrUlEQVQoz42SW26cMBSG2WIfu41uIC9dQ/dUqS+R0qrSKEoyzAzGHgy2j2/YQH9Dm6aJiGrBsfnNZ59bxVvWCSGvV962rGkulzPnbXO+YMU5L8Ll3DTNqa5bxoSA1g5Df/P5y4ePnypudC1lqxU5l8ZxjLGYMq+LGFNRf+uw+ILS3D883t5VgsyxlyaGeVnwvDPABu+MdYcjk0pDqfwYlbdjzviYd8Y0TT4EpdT3++O3n49f7w6MMTIEeLwSwbk9NKWktOZd/9TwHw+nmgnnrDEmhFDFnKS1O/AyzbP3nnFxqNnTmVnSRf0TYJVy7ndgeIsUCdmza2/IarIpZbAbX+A8zdK+cXvLUErdoE7w03vcMb3eXyrMg3d/4VVFnKiMIqsMAXveeQ3j1c/wum2I5KAGQznnlVw2V+e3N+MtiQO8+qmt67UJ40jW5bV+PsY8Tbuwi9GXTkJJTDdoJAah4vfxRSKmF/YfGKVGNpmQvJMAcM3yf6PA8Mp5F3woDRgD+hlxWOfQVSiytVg62E3f7BZRZV0g8kRoGoLHqzWb1esATwTdeF8wjyPXI3DTLzXjZO0czVXXAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;transistor&quot;
        title=&quot;transistor&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/fcda8/transistor.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/12f09/transistor.png 148w,
/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/e4a3f/transistor.png 295w,
/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/fcda8/transistor.png 590w,
/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/efc66/transistor.png 885w,
/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/c83ae/transistor.png 1180w,
/static/59c9c855cf1594c01aeca9cf9c7ccefe/79ee6/transistor.png 3133w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what do transistors and silicon chips have to do with anything? Well, this revolutionized computing in the last 50 years, making technology ubiquitous, and shaping the world as we know it. Why is that? Well squeezing more transistors onto a chip (the brain of your smartphone or computer), gives you speed, and a reduction in required power for the same level of processing (an extreme oversimplification, but you get the idea).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, this law has stood the test of time. Moore revised the forecast to a rate of every two years in 1975, and has proven accurate time and again. The law is said to be responsible for technological change, acting as a guide for the semiconductor industry, in long term research and development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to remind you how far we’ve come, the Intel 4004 chip released in 1971 had 2,250 transistors and supported 4kb of memory. The popular AMD Ryzen 7 3700X has 3.8 million transistors, and supports up to 128 GB (a whopping 128,000,000kb)! Not only has this change led to increases in computing power, but squeezing transistors into smaller chips has enabled the explosion of smartphones. Modern-day smartphones have orders of magnitude more power than supercomputers in 1960.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though this seems a law of physics, it’s really a law of economics. It tells us that each new chip will have twice the transistors, and therefore compute the capability of the previous generation, at the same cost of production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what? We know technology has changed a lot - what’s your point?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, in recent years, it’s claimed Moore’s law has begun to slow. If this is true, this could lead to stagnant technological progression. No bigger and better iPhones. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.itrs2.net/uploads/4/9/7/7/49775221/irc-itrs-mtm-v2_3.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;According to a report by ITRS&lt;/a&gt; (roadmap for semiconductors) - which includes Intel and Samsung - transistors may stop shrink as soon as 2021. It will therefore cease to be economically viable to make them smaller, holding Moore’s law. It makes sense as well right? We can only reduce a physical transistor down to a point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current cadence of change has certainly changed (known as the shrink factor), this used to be 2x every 2 years, it’s now roughly (0.6). This equates to roughly 1/.6 more transistors every 2 years. However, as Jim Keller points out (legendary chip designer), there are thousands of innovations that go into the advancements of chips. Each of which has its own diminishing return curves. Therefore, each of their innovations reach a point of plateau. At which point, other innovations take precedence/new inventions come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about the question of how small can a transistor be? Well, modern transistors are roughly 1000 x 1000 x 1000 atoms small. Quantum effects come into play roughly 2^10, so in theory, we could reach 10 x 10 x 10 (1m times smaller). We’ve all heard about quantum computing, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, the method of shrinking is one thing. However, there are thousands of technologies involved. Purely shrinking has not yet reached the laws of physics. Neglecting to mention this process involves chemistry, material science, geometry, meteorology, etc. Additionally, advancements in computing power don’t only come through hardware advancements. Not to mention the fact that AI has exploded, who knows what interpreting data around computer processing and hardware capabilities could bring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s the answer? Well, nobody knows. Perhaps it depends on which glass you drink from. Personally, I’m hopeful technology won’t stop anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The One That Got Away, Chris Ryan]]></title><description><![CDATA[I read this book a long while back when I was roughly 15 or 16. In fact, it’s one of only 2 books I read before the age of 21, at which…]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev/the-one-that-got-away/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://garethveale.dev/the-one-that-got-away/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I read this book a long while back when I was roughly 15 or 16. In fact, it’s one of only 2 books I read before the age of 21, at which point I developed an interest in reading. The reason I read it back then is the exact reason I chose to re-read it - I cannot put it down. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had an interest in military history, particularly WW2 and special forces. Coming from a military family, and with a dad that spent the better part of life serving, it was natural I would develop an interest. Couple that with a gripping tale of tremendous courage, persistence, and grit, and I’m left with a book that doesn’t feel like reading. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the true story of a member of a SAS patrol that gets compromised deep behind enemy lines in Iraq, during the first Gulf war. Chris Ryan and his squad initiate their E&amp;#x26;E (escape and evasion) plan, making a run for the Syrian border. Inevitably, they’re met with tons of challenges, and Ryan is the only one to successfully escape. This is an immense display of what the human body is capable of when the mind has the grit and determination to never give up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read this with ease the first time, and I enjoyed it, even more, the second. However, I only rate it a 7 as not everyone will find this as interesting as me, and am therefore less likely to recommend it. If you have any interest in military history, do yourself a favor and pick this one up.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[3 Books Everyone Should Read]]></title><description><![CDATA[I recently made a video about the top 3 books I recommend everyone take the time to read and absorb. I made this selection based on the…]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev/top-3-recommended-books/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://garethveale.dev/top-3-recommended-books/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I recently made a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i2AFJoB8RVA&amp;#x26;t=237s&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; about the top 3 books I recommend everyone take the time to read and absorb. I made this selection based on the level of impact these books had on my life. Firstly, by shaping how I think. Secondly, by teaching me lessons I feel are invaluable, that I find myself continuously referring back to. Below are my brief thoughts on what I believe you can expect from each. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Meditations, Marcus Aurelius (Gregory Hays translation)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a collection of thoughts or journal entries of a Roman emperor by the name of Marcus Aurelius. He was not only one of the most powerful men in history, but also an avid Stoic. These entries, though likely not intended for mass consumption, offer some incredible wisdom, and substantial teachings from the school of Stoicism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a large fan of Stoicism, this book immediately piqued my interest. Though FWIW, if you haven’t heard of this school of Philosophy it’s not important. The passages here, in my humble opinion, will help everyone live a more balanced, fulfilling life. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you simply read this for the knowledge that you’re reading the journal entries of a Roman Emporer, it’s pretty neat. I recommend the Gregory Hay’s translation, it seems agreed to be the easiest to interpret. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Man’s Search for Meaning, Viktor Frankl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next on the list is a book written by a Holocaust and Auswitchz survivor. Being a psychiatrist, he records an interesting account of his time within the concentration camps. He explores the mental psyche of those around him, how it affected them, and shares his observations of what he believes to be the reason some survived, and others gave up. As you would expect this is not an easy read, though in my opinion books that aren’t, often offer the best lessons. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read this if you want to feel more appreciation for the simple things in life, and for an education on how to handle adversity, difficulties, and challenges. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Not Fade Away, Lawrence Shames and Peter Barton&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, is a book I’ve read a few times over. This one is less intense as the others, though that’s not to say the lessons within are any less important. This book explores the life of the very successful founder of Liberty Media (an extremely powerful and influential media company). After being diagnosed with terminal cancer, he spends time reflecting on his life with an author (Lawrence Shames), discussing his achievements, experiences, and the lessons he learnt throughout. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a candid take on the road to success, and ultimately the trade-offs that may be experienced as a result. Peter opens up about the challenges he faced raising children while building and managing a business empire. It’s an important account of what can happen if time isn’t spent considering life satisfaction over fortune and fame. Pick this up for humor and wisdom, but be prepared to become pretty emotionally invested. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Build and deploy your personal blog using GatsbyJS and GH Pages]]></title><description><![CDATA[I recently rebuilt my website using a scalable architecture, leveraging modern web technologies (Flask, Docker, React) enabling me 
to host…]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev/builder-your-own-gatsby-blog/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://garethveale.dev/builder-your-own-gatsby-blog/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I recently rebuilt my website using a scalable architecture, leveraging modern web technologies (Flask, Docker, React) enabling me
to host multiple applications under the same deployment (post on this incoming). One of these applications being the blog you’re reading now, built with Gatsby JS.
This post is to show you how easy this is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Familarity with JS, React adn GraphQL is a prerequisite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is GatsbyJS?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gatsbyjs.org/&quot;&gt;Gatsby&lt;/a&gt; is a React-based static site generator, powered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://graphql.org/&quot;&gt;GraphQL&lt;/a&gt;. It weaves together parts of React -
specifically webpack, react-router, GraphQL (among others) - into an easy to use development framework.
The term static site generator may be a bit misleading, Gatsby is far more like a modern front-end framework
and can be used to build progressive web apps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It uses powerful preconfiguration to build a website that uses only static files for incredibly fast page loads,
service workers, code splitting, server-side rendering, intelligent image loading, asset optimization, and data prefetching - all out of the box. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After writing your code Gatsby transforms it into a directory with a single HTML file and your static assets and this folder is uploaded to your hosting provider - voila.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Introducing Gatsby Starter Blog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tons of pre-built Gatsby templates available to be cloned from github offering you the chance to build
and deploy faster. In order to create our blog we’re going to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby-starter-blog&quot;&gt;gatsby-starter-blog&lt;/a&gt;, giving us a pre-built blog template that can be modified as we please. This template uses markdown files as blog posts, auto generating
pages (and slugs) for each of the ‘posts’. GraphQL is leveraged to query the static files for each of the requested items, resulting in a super fast final product. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get started you’ll want to iensure you have a recent version of Node.js installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install gatsby&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;npm install gatsby&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now clone down the gatsby-starter-blog repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;gatsby new my-blog-starter https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby-starter-blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fire up the site and start developing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cd my-blog-starter/
gatsby develop&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice in the terminal the site is running at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8000&quot;&gt;http://localhost:8000&lt;/a&gt;, and you can also access &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:8000__graphql&quot;&gt;http://localhost:8000__graphql&lt;/a&gt; to practice
querying your data using GraphQL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some pointers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gatsby-config.js as the name states houses the site configurations, you can add additional gatsby plugins here &amp;#x26; modify site metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gatsby-node.js contains the graphql query and js code that constructs a page for each markdown post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog posts are written in markdown and each live within a directoy, the name of which is used as the page slug&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Deploying to GH pages (for free)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a repo to house your website ready for deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, add the GitHub repo name to your gatsby-config.js file. Assuming your GitHub repo is called ‘myBlog’…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;jsg&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-jsg&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-jsg&quot;&gt;module.exports = {
  pathPrefix: &amp;quot;/myBlog&amp;quot;,
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, add a custom command deploy to your package.json file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;js&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;scripts&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;deploy&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;gatsby build --prefix-paths &amp;amp;&amp;amp; gh-pages -d public&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a deploy command that creates a static version of your site with the prefix of /myBlog/ for every URL and then pushes the public directory using the gh-pages plugin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, add the GitHub repository as the origin remote to your Gatsby Git repository by running the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;js&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;git remote add origin https&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;username&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;github&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;com&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;myBlog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To build and deploy your site run the custom script&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;js&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-js&quot;&gt;npm run deploy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will push the data to the gh-pages branch of your repository, without adding any commits to other branches. Almost instantly after the push, you can view your served pages on username.github.io/myBlog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you own a domain you can associate it with this hosted GH repo to change the default domain - &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/managing-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; link has detailed instructions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[1984, George Orwell]]></title><description><![CDATA[We are the dead… you are the dead.  That quote stuck with me after reading this novel, particularly because several friends had mentioned it…]]></description><link>https://garethveale.dev/1984/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://garethveale.dev/1984/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are the dead… you are the dead. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That quote stuck with me after reading this novel, particularly because several friends had mentioned it when discussing our thoughts. It didn’t strike me to be particularly significant at first, but after I finished the book and pondered the messages portrayed by Orwell I came to realise it’s importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put off reading this book for a long while and I immediately came to regret that decision. Within the first 50 pages, the horror of the dystopia begins to set in and I couldn’t stop turning pages. It both terrified and excited me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more I thought about this novel the more I understood. I’m shocked by the number of parallels that can be drawn between this novel and modern-day society. Not only in countries that have adopted an authoritarian political ideology, but also in the west. Mainstream and social media platforms threaten our capacity for freethinking,
commercial and political interests influence the messaging, elected officials misrepresent the truth, government agencies attempt to and sometimes do invade the privacy of the individuals. Our digital privacy becomes more at risk as data becomes the new age oil. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1984 is a political statement, a simple warning to mankind. Orwell must’ve felt society beginning to assault his personal freedom, failing to defend our most precious right, the right to have our own thoughts. He wasn’t wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read that Orwell intended to name the book ‘The Last Man in Europe’, as a tribute to the quality that distinguished man from the world around him, namely his ability to think for himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between Winston and Julia took me by surprise, making it all the more enticing. Orwell lures you into a seemingly hopeful drop in an otherwise harrowing pond. Suffice to say it doesn’t last very long, but makes for a wicked read. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the reading of the book gifted to Winston to be a little mundane and skipped large parts of it, but that didn’t stop me from reading until the end. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘In a free society, it is not always important that individuals reason well, it is
sufficient that they reason; from their individual thought, freedom is born.’ - &lt;strong&gt;Montesquieu&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend reading this, even (I suppose especially) if you’re like me and don’t read much fiction. Solid 9/10.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>